Hi, this is Matt Baker. On this channel,
I've done a lot of who would be king
videos, such as who would be king of
France, who would be Zar of Russia, etc.
But in all of these cases, they were
just fun whatifs because the chances of
any of these countries actually
restoring their monarchies is pretty
much zero. However, these days, there is
in fact some talk of one particular
monarchy being restored, and that is of
course Iran due to the recent uprising
there. Although it is still very
uncertain as to whether or not the
current regime will fall or even if it
does whether or not the people would
want a monarchy again, Iran does in fact
have a monarchy in waiting. So today I'm
going to share a bit of the history of
that monarchy and show you who the
current members of their royal family
are. But first, if you want to stay up
to date with what's happening in Iran, I
highly recommend that you sign up for
Ground News. It's the website and app
that I myself use whenever I want to see
how important events are being covered
in the media. You see, for every
breaking story, they give you access to
dozens, sometimes hundreds of different
sources so that you can compare how
things are being reported in different
locations as well as on different sides
of the political spectrum. For example,
when it comes to the situation in Iran,
Ground News recently gathered hundreds
of articles about the emergency UN
meeting in which the US warned Iran that
all options are on the table. Using the
app, you can see how left-leaning news
outlets were more likely to focus on the
human rights violations taking place,
whereas right-leaning outlets were more
likely to focus on the US's role in
solving the problem. But perhaps more
importantly, Ground News helps you
decide which ones out of all of the many
sources are considered to be the most
factual using third-party rankings. They
even tell you how each news organization
is funded, which helps highlight
potential biases. And they do all of
this with easy to understand charts. So,
as you can probably guess, I really like
Ground News. So, don't wait. Subscribe
now by going to ground.news/charts
news/charts
or by using the link in the description
or pinned comment. Be sure to use my
link so that you can save 40% off
unlimited access to their Vantage plan.
Again, that's ground.news/charts.
Okay, so the first thing you need to
know is that up until 1979, Iran or
Persia as it was once called had some
form of monarchy for over 2,500 years
going all the way back to Cyrus the
Great. That's a really long time. So, I
won't be going back that far, at least
not in this video. Instead, I'm going to
start around 500 years ago with Ismile I
of the Safavid dynasty. The Safavidids
rose to power around the same time as
the Ottomans and are notable in that
they were the first Persian dynasty to
rule Persia since before the Islamic
conquests. So basically, after around
850 years of either Arab or Turo Mongol
rule, the Persian monarchy was finally
once again Persian. They as well as all
subsequent monarchs thus used the title
Sha which is the ancient Persian word
for king or emperor. The Safavidids
reached their peak during the reign of
Abbas the Great who helped solidify Shia
Islam as the main religion of Iran, a
situation that continues to this day. In
total, the Safavids reigned for around
230 years. Although near the end, most
of their territory was lost to the
Afghan Hots as well as to the Ottomans
and Russians. But then came the slaveet
turned general Nadir Shaw who conquered
it all back plus a little more. He
established a new dynasty, but one that
did not last long after he himself was
assassinated. Next came the Zans, but
they were quickly replaced by the
Kajars, who moved the capital to Thran
and ruled for the entirety of the 19th
century. Within the Khajar family tree,
you might recognize these two princesses
because they went viral in this century
as examples of how beauty standards are
constantly changing. But it was their
brother, Mosafar Adin, who truly made a
mark on Iranian history. Just prior to
his death, he approved of the country's
first ever constitution, which involved
the creation of an elected parliament.
However, when his son Muhammad Ali
became Sha, he reversed course, ushering
in a brief period known as the minor
tyranny. But after just one year,
proconstitutional forces were able to
depose him in what's called the triumph
of Thran, replacing him with his son
Ahmmed, who at the time was just 11. But
Ahmad was weak and allowed foreign
powers like the UK and Russia to
basically do whatever they wanted. Thus
in 1921 there was a coup in which a
military leader named Resa Khan
basically took over taking the title of
prime minister but then in 1925 being
declared the new Sha. By this point he
had adopted the surname Palavi chosen
because it was the name of a language
spoken in the region in ancient times.
He helped modernize the country and is
the one who first encouraged diplomats
to use the name Iran rather than Persia.
This was important because not all
Iranians are ethnically Persian.
However, World War II led to his
downfall because although Iran was
technically neutral, it had close ties
to Germany. And thus, in 1941, the
Allies invaded the country, forged Reza
to resign, and replaced him with his
firstborn son, Muhammad Reza. Muhammad
Reza reigned for 38 years, during which
time he continued his father's
modernization of Iran, launching his
white revolution in 1963. Take note that
the word white in this context has
nothing to do with race, but was rather
chosen to symbolize the peaceful nature
of the changes. Among the changes were
increased rights for women and
minorities. Also, during the Palavi
period, there was a greater emphasis put
on Iran's ancient history rather than on
its Islamic history. For example, in
1971, the country celebrated the 2500th
anniversary of the founding of the
Persian Empire by Cyrus the Great,
building this famous landmark to
commemorate it. In 1979, there was a
major revolution in which the Sha was
exiled and Iran was transformed into an
Islamic republic. Since then, there have
been two supreme leaders, Ayatollah
Kmeni. Ayatollah being a title used by
certain Shia clerics and Ayatollah Kam.
Take note that while the two names are
quite similar, they are spelled and
pronounced differently and there is no
familial relationship between the two
men. However, in the future, there could
be a supreme leader that is related to a
previous one, as one of Kam's sons and
one of Kmeni's grandsons are both seen
as potential successors. But if the
regime falls and if the Palavi monarchy
were to be reinstated, again, those are
two very big ifs, the answer to who
would be king, or rather Sha is actually
quite simple. It would be Reza, the
firstborn son of Muhammad Reza, who
would become Reza II. Take note that
Muhammad Reza was married three times.
First of all, to Princess Faia of Egypt.
That marriage produced one daughter,
Shaunes, but ended in divorce as it was
quite clearly just a political pairing
that neither side was happy with. The
Sha's second wife was Sarah, the
daughter of an Iranian diplomat. She was
supposedly the love of his life. But
when it became clear that she was unable
to bear him children, that marriage also
ended in divorce. Muhammad Reza thus
married for a third time to Farah, who
became known as Empress Farah, when the
pair were crowned Emperor and Empress
during an elaborate ceremony in 1967.
It is she who is the mother of Reza who
was named Crown Prince during that same
ceremony at age 6. But then of course
the monarchy was abolished in 1979 when
Reza was 17. His father died shortly
after this and thus he declared himself
to be the new king albeit in exile.
Since that time he has mostly lived in
the United States. It was there that he
met and married fellow Iranian Yasmine
with whom he has three daughters.
Although the former constitution
stipulates that only males can inherit
the throne, he considers his eldest
daughter Noir to be his heir. To date,
she has not yet married, although her
younger sister Iman has. Just last year,
she married Bradley Sherman, a Jewish
American tech entrepreneur. Now, sadly,
two of Reza's siblings died young. Ali
from suicide in 2011 and Leila from an
overdose in 2001, which might also have
been a suicide. Ali's only child is a
daughter. So that means that if Raa were
to become king under the old
constitution, the one that requires
heirs to be from the male line only,
that would mean that the next person in
line would actually be this guy over
here, Dav Pali. But again, he has only
daughters. So after that we'd have to
look at his brothers or go all the way
back to the descendants of these guys up
here. Now there is another option and
that is to go back to the Kajgers who
reigned before the Palavis. Although I
doubt there's many Iranians who actually
want to do that. When Ahmmed died in
exile in 1930, his only son Farun was
just 8 years old. and therefore it was
his brother Muhammad Hassan who had
previously been crowned prince who
claimed to be the rightful Shaw. After
his death, the claim then passed to Fun,
but he never pursued it, having settled
into a nice life in Switzerland. Since
he married a Swiss commoner, his
children are not considered eligible.
And therefore, the next person to have a
claim was Muhammad Hassan's son Hamid,
who then passed it on to his son,
Muhammad Hassan II, who is the current
Kajger heir today. Although, take note
that it is a cousin from another branch
of the tree who currently serves as head
of house, which is maybe a role that
involves taking calls from journalists
or attending funerals. I'm actually not
really sure. Okay, so that was a look at
some of the former monarchs of Iran as
well as their descendants today. Let me
know in the comments what you think
Iran's future holds. And don't forget to
check out Ground News. Thanks for
watching.